A Guide to the National Association of Alcoholism and Drug Abuse Counselors, 1970-2000
Library of Virginia
Library of Virginia
National Association of Alcoholism and Drug Abuse Counselors, 1970-2000
Library of Virginia
36851; 37959
58.05 cubic feet (126 boxes).
National Association of Alcoholism and Drug Abuse Counselors
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open to research.
Acquisition Information
Gift of NAADAC Education and Research Foundation, Arlington, Virginia
Biographical Information
The National Association of Alcoholism Counselors and Trainers (NAACT) held its first organizational meeting in Washington DC, in June, 1974, during a period when the alcoholism field was experiencing rapid growth as a result of a new federal program of grants for treatment, rehabilitation, and prevention of alcohol abuse and alcoholism. Matthew J. Rose, a retired government official and resident of Arlington, VA, led the effort to establish a national organization, and became Executive Director of the new association. Counselors sought recognition of their profession in the expanding field through nationally recognized certification standards and procedures. Advocacy through a national organization was perceived as necessary to advance the profession. Coinciding with efforts to organize a national association of counselors, the Virginia Association of Alcoholism Counselors (VAAC) was being formed. Individuals active at the national level were prominent in the Virginia association, including Virginia residents Edward Riordan and Mel Schulstad. The Alcohol and Drug Abuse Rehabilitation Program (ADERP) at Virginia Commonwealth University, under Marcia Lawton, Ph.D., and the Greater Richmond Council on Alcoholism and Drug Abuse (GRCADA) also contributed to the organizational effort. The National Association of Alcoholism Counsleors and Trainers in June, 1976, changed its name to National Association of Alcoholism Counselors (NAAC), in a move to provide a sole focus on counselors.
In August 1982, the board of directors changed the name to the National Association of Alcoholism and Drug Abuse Counselors (NAADAC), then adopted new by-laws providing for individual membership in addition to affiliation by state associations. Membership grew to 14,000 with affiliates in all 50 states. The Association played an integral role in the effort to establish a nationally recognized set of standards and procedures for the credentialing of counselors, culminating in 1990 when the NAADAC Certification Commission was established to administer the credential of National Certified Addiction Counselor. Some 8,000 counselors qualified initially for the certification.
Scope and Content
Records, 1970-2000, of the National Association of Alcoholism and Drug Abuse Counselors (NAADAC), consisting of its National Counselor Certification files, National Commission for Accreditation files, Alcohol and Drug Abuse Rehabilitation (ADERP) files, ADERP/Richmond Focus files, ADERP/National files, Virginia Certification files, Greater Richmond Council on Alcoholism and Drug Abuse (GRCADA) files, NAADAC General Historical files, Board Mailings files, Correspondence/Miscellaneous files, Executive Director's files, NAADAC Foundation files, Government Relations/Public Policy Conference files, Government Relations/Treatment Works files, Government Relations/General files, and Publications.
National Counselor Certification files include certification reports, committee reports, minutes, publications, organization by-laws, NAADAC Certification Commission meeting materials and minutes, and correspondence. National Commission for Accreditation files consist of correspondence, organization by-laws and information on hospitals and alcoholism programs. Alcohol and Drug Abuse Rehabilitation Program files consist of history, quarterly reports, Virginia Commonwealth University courses and students, correspondence, plans, programs, publications, and directories. ADERP/Virginia Association of Alcoholism and Drug Abuse Counselors (VAADAC) files include history, newsletters, conference information, programs, articles, and educational information. ADERP/Richmond Focus files include Richmond Focus files and publications. ADERP/National files consist of information on hospitals and alcoholism programs, guidelines, reports, organizations information, educational information, correspondence, surveys, articles, and publications. Virginia Certification files include accreditation information, conference information, proposals, correspondence, reports, educational information, organization by-laws and information, and publications. Greater Richmond Council on Alcoholism and Drug Abuse (GRCADA) files consist of history, constitution, by-laws, membership lists, board minutes, correspondence, and newsletters.
NAADAC General Historical files include history, mailings, correspondence, organizations information, workshops, conference information, pins, buttons, and stamps. Board Mailings files include correspondence, meeting agendas, board minutes, financial budgets and information, by-laws, conference minutes and information, reports, and manuals. Correspondence/Miscellaneous files consist of correspondence, conference information, and legislative information. Executive Director's files include organization by-laws, membership rosters and directories, conference information and minutes, committee funding and membership, financial budgets and information, board minutes, training programs and surveys. NAADAC Foundation files consist of correspondence, board minutes, grant applications, financial information, as well as records for the NAADAC Education and Research Foundation (NERF). Government Relations/Public Policy Conferences files includes legislative conference materials and minutes, correspondence, reports, and biographies. Government Relations/Treatment Works! files consist of correspondence, brochures, photographs, programs, congressional briefings, press, releases, agendas, and notes. Government Relations/General files consist of fact sheets, position papers, correspondence, agendas, mailings, board and committee meetings, conference information, articles, notes, newsletters, legislation, congressional hearings, and proclamations. Publications include the Counselor, the Journal, the US Journal, The Bottom Line, and other books, manuals, and journals.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged
I. National Counselor Certification
II. National Commission for Accreditation
III. Alcohol and Drug Abuse Rehabilitation Program (ADERP)
IV. ADERP/Virginia Association of Alcoholism and Drug Abuse Counselors (VAADAC)
V. ADERP/Richmond Focus
VI. ADERP/National Files
VII. Virginia Certification
VIII. Greater Richmond Council on Alcoholism and Drug Abuse (GRCADA)
IX. NAADAC General Historical
X. Board Mailings
XI. Correspondence/Miscellaneous
XII. Executive Director's Files
XIII. NAADAC Foundation
XIV. Government Relations/Public Policy Conference
XV. Government Relations/Treatment Works
XVI. Government Relations/General
XVII. Publications
Contents List
- National Counselor Certification - Certification and Credentialing (Box 1-2)
  - Proposed National Standard for Alcoholism Counselors--Final Report, 30 August 1974 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Finger Panel--Subcommittee on Organization and Administration (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Birch & Davis Report (Development of Model Professional Standards for Counselor Credentialing) (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Littlejohn Report (Proposed national standard for alcoholism counselors (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Drug Program Review (August 1978)--credentialing (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Certification for chemical dependency practicioners/chemical dependency training program accrediters (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Resources Bulletin (January 1979)--Credentialing: A State Effort (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - California Handbook on Certification (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Certification--discussion (Box 1, Folder 9-11)
  - National certification--NCAC (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Development of competency examinations for alcoholism counselors--Educational Testing Service (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Certification process (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Training and examination (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Licensing of alcohol and drug counselors in the states (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Task Force on Substance Abuse Certification (Box 2, Folder 1-3)
  - Credentialing of drug abuse treatment and rehabilitation workers--summery of the status report--February 1975 (University Research Corp.) (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Credentialing of alcoholism counselors--Report no. IV: Phase I Report--March 1981 (A. T. Kearney) (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Certification of substance abuse counselors--August 1991 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Certification--Ad Hoc Committee--Memphis (Box 2, Folder 7)
- National Counselor Certification - Reciprocity (Box 2)
  - Certification Reciprocity Consortium (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - CRC/AODA (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - CRC/ICRC (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - National Certification Reciprocity Consortium (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - NCRC/NAADAC Relations (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Reciprocity meeting--Houston, TX--16-18 November 1978 (Box 2, Folder 13)
- National Counselor Certification - Organizations (Box 2-7)
  - CSTAA--Certification of alcoholism counselors (microfiche) (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - NAAC Executive Committee meeting 31 October 1978 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - NAACT educational program (Box 2, Folder 16-18)
  - NCAADACCB--Application for accreditation (Box 3, Folder 1-2)
  - NCAADACCB--Correspondence--to 1987 (Box 3, Folder 3-4)
  - NCAADACCB--Correspondence 1987 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - NCAADACCB--Minutes 1979-1989 (Box 3, Folder 6-7)
  - NCAADACCB--Memos/letters 1986-1989 (Box 3, Folder 8-9)
  - NCAADACCB--Conference call minutes and Executive Committee members (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - NCAADACCB--Miscellaneous (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - NCAADACCB--By-laws (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - NCAADACCB--1988 elections (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - NCAADACCB--Expenses (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - NCAADACCB--Paid members 1986-1989 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - NCAADACCB--Criteria for accreditation of certifying bodies (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - NCAADACCB--Certificates (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - NCAADACCB--Correspondence 1988 (Box 4, Folder 5-6)
  - Counselor Development in the States: NCAE's Findings and Response (October 1978) (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - National Commission on Credentialing of Alcoholism Counselors (Box 4, Folder 8-9)
  - National Commission on Credentialing of Alcoholism Counselors (NCCAC) 1978 (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - National Commission on Credentialing of Alcoholism Counselors (NCCAC) 1979-1981 (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - NCCAC--From DEH reading file (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - NCCAC correspondence (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - NCCAC-NIAAA negotiations (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - NCCAC--Three year plan of action 1978 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Initial meeting--NCCAC commissioners--23-24 May 1978 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - NCCAC standards (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - NCCAC--Memos 1979 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - NCCAC--Board of Directors reorganization--August 1980 and NIAAA notification of Kearney award (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - NCCAC--Committee assignments (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - NCCAC--General (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - NCCAC--Application for accreditation (Box 5, Folder 8-9)
  - NCCAC--Background (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - NCCAC--Board meeting 27 June 1979 (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - NCCAC--By-laws (Box 5, Folder 12)
  - NCCAC--Legal affairs--Application to do business in CT (Box 5, Folder 13)
  - NCCAC--Legal affairs--IRS 501(c)3 application (Box 5, Folder 14)
  - NCCAC--Minute--Detroit meeting 30 October 1978 (Box 5, Folder 15)
  - NCCAC--Request for Proposal (RFP) No. NIA-0024-- "Credentialing of Alcoholism Counselors" (Box 5, Folder 16)
  - NCCAC--D. C. corporation reports (Box 5, Folder 17)
  - NCCAC--Speech outline (Box 5, Folder 18)
  - NCCAC--Press release 1978 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - NCCAC-NIAAA meeting 20 November 1978 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - NCCAC--Support for (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - NCCAC--Executive Committee minutes--Memphis 7 August 1978 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - NCCAC--Minutes--23-24 May 1978--ADPA office, Washington, D.C. (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - NCCAC Board expansion (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - NCCAC expansion plan--30 October 1978- (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - NCCAC--1979 consultants (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - NCCAC--Three year plan of action (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - NCCAC--RFP/Task Force (Box 6, Folder 10)
  - NCCAC--Request for Proposal (RFP) no. NIA 80-0003-- "Credentialing of Alcoholism Counselors" (Box 6, Folder 11-12)
  - National Register of Credentialed Alcoholism Counselors, Credentialed Drug Abuse Counselors, and Credentialed Alcoholism and Drug Abuse Counselors (Box 6, Folder unfoldered)
  - NCCAC--Technical Proposal (Box 6, Folder unfoldered)
  - NIAAA--Contract negotiations (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - NIDA Task Force meeting--November 1978 (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - VAAC certification board by-laws (Box 7, Folder 3)
- National Counselor Certification - Virginia Certification Reports (Box 7)
  - Report of the Virginia Commission for Professional and Occupational Regulation 1974 (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - Joint Subcommittee on Alcohol and Drug Abuse--Interim Report to the Virginia General Assembly 19 January 1976 (Box 7, Folder 5-6)
  - Final Virginia report--Legislative professional staff project (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - Statement of the Virginia Association of Drug Programs at the public hearing of drug counselors 4 August 1980 (Box 7, Folder 8)
  - License--August 1991 (Box 7, Folder 9)
  - Drug Counselor Educational Advisory Committee (Box 7, Folder 10-11)
  - Educational Advisory Committee--alcohol (Box 7, Folder 12-14)
- National Counselor Certification - Education (Box 7A-8)
  - Addiction Counselors Training Program (Box 7A, Folder 1)
  - Application and Instructions for Providers of Continuing Education for Certified Counselors in the United States (Box 7A, Folder 2)
  - Clinical Issues Manual for Alcohol and Other Drug Abuse Counselors (Box 7A, Folder 3-4)
  - Education Working Group-1991 (Box 7A, Folder 5)
  - NAADAC Certification Commission certificates (Box 7A, Folder 6)
  - NCAC Certification Review Manual (Box 7A, Folder 7)
  - NCAC Certification Review Workshops (Box 7A, Folder 8)
  - NCAC Deadline Reminders (Box 7A, Folder 9)
  - Project for Addiction Counselor Training (Box 7A, Folder 10)
  - OSAP-NAADAC Survey of AODA Counselor Certification and Training (executive and management summaries only) 1990 (Box 7B, Folder 1)
  - OSAP-NAADAC Survey of AODA Counselor Certification and Training (full text)-1990 (Box 7B, Folder 2-3)
  - Oral Examination Handbook for Addiction Counselor Certification Boards (Box 7B, Folder 4)
  - Basics of Addiction Counseling: Desk Reference and Study Guide (Box 7B, Folder unfoldered)
  - NAADAC Study Guide and Desk Reference on Addiction Counseling (Box 7B, Folder unfoldered)
  - National Alcohol and Drug Abuse Education (Box 8, Folder 1-2)
  - Train the Trainer workshop--12-13 September 1978 (Box 8, Folder 3)
- National Counselor Certification - Miscellaneous (Box 8)
  - Alcoholism Counselor--Functions (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - Careers (Box 8, Folder 5)
  - Competencies (Box 8, Folder 6-7)
  - Concerned Person Notebook (Box 8, Folder 8)
  - Delivery service (Box 8, Folder 9-10)
  - Minnesota Chemical Dependency Association, Inc. (Box 8, Folder 11)
  - Prevention specialist (Box 8, Folder 12)
  - Role of the alcoholism counselor (Box 8, Folder 13)
  - Sapp contract (Box 8, Folder 14)
  - Science Management Corp. (Box 8, Folder 15)
  - Vitaes (Box 8, Folder 16)
  - Willcut, Roger--Correspondence (Box 8, Folder 17)
- National Counselor Certification - NAADAC Certification Commission - Meetings (Box 8-8A)
  - (Box 8, Folder 17)
  - 1990-NAADAC National Credential Information Meeting-Chicago, IL-14-15 July (Box 8A, Folder 1)
  - 1990-NAADAC Certification Commission Meeting-Indianapolis, IN-September (Box 8A, Folder 2)
- National Counselor Certification - NAADAC Certification Commission - Meetings-Winter (Box 8A-8B)
  - 1991-Winter meeting-Indianapolis, IN-January (Box 8A, Folder 3)
  - 1992-Winter meeting-Washington, DC-January-February (Box 8A, Folder 4)
  - 1993-Winter meeting-Washington, DC-February (Box 8A, Folder 5)
  - 1994-Winter meeting-Washington, DC-February (Box 8A, Folder 6)
  - 1995-Winter meeting-Rosslyn, VA-February (Box 8A, Folder 7)
  - 1995-Winter meeting-Rosslyn, VA-February (backup book) (Box 8A, Folder 8-9)
  - 1996-Winter meeting-Rosslyn, VA-February (Box 8A, Folder 10-11)
  - 1997-Winter meeting-Rosslyn, VA-February-March (Box 8A, Folder 12)
  - 1998-Winter meeting-Rosslyn, VA-February (Box 8B, Folder 1-2)
  - 2000-Winter meeting-Washington, DC-February (Box 8B, Folder 3)
- National Counselor Certification - NAADAC Certification Commission - Meetings - Summer (Box 8B-8C)
  - 1991-Summer meeting-San Antonio, TX-June (Box 8B, Folder 4)
  - 1992-Summer meeting-Crystal City, VA-July (Box 8B, Folder 5)
  - 1993-Summer meeting-Chicago, IL-June (Box 8B, Folder 6)
  - 1994-Summer meeting-San Diego, CA-July (Box 8B, Folder 7)
  - 1994-Summer meeting-San Diego, CA-July-Supplement-National Board for Certified Counselors, Inc. (NBCC) (Box 8B, Folder 8)
  - 1995-Summer meeting-Orlando, FL-July (Box 8B, Folder 9)
  - 1996-Summer meeting-Minneapolis, MN-July (Box 8B, Folder 10)
  - 1997-Summer meeting-San Francisco, CA-July (Box 8B, Folder 11)
  - 1998-Summer meeting-Chicago, IL-July (Box 8C, Folder 1)
  - 1999-Summer meeting-Philadelphia, PA-May (Box 8C, Folder 2)
- National Counselor Certification - NAADAC Certification Commission - Meetings - Teleconferences (Box 8C)
  - 1991-Teleconference agenda and minutes-1 February (Box 8C, Folder 3)
  - 1991-Teleconference agenda and minutes-7 March (Box 8C, Folder 4)
  - 1991-Teleconference agenda and minutes-28 March (Box 8C, Folder 5)
  - 1991-Teleconference materials and minutes-26 April (Box 8C, Folder 6)
  - 1991-Teleconference agenda and minutes-17 May (Box 8C, Folder 7)
  - 1991-Teleconference minutes-31 May (Box 8C, Folder 8)
  - 1991-Teleconference agenda and minutes-14 June (Box 8C, Folder 9)
  - 1991-Teleconference agenda and minutes-18 July (Box 8C, Folder 10)
  - 1991-Teleconference memorandum, agenda, and minutes-23 July (Box 8C, Folder 11)
  - 1991-Teleconference agenda and minutes-23 September (Box 8C, Folder 12)
  - 1991-Teleconference minutes and procedure policy-28 October (Box 8C, Folder 13)
  - 1991-Teleconference materials-9 December (Box 8C, Folder 14)
  - 1991-Teleconference minutes-30 March (Box 8C, Folder 15)
  - 1992-Teleconference minutes-12 April (Box 8C, Folder 16)
  - 1992-Teleconference materials and minutes-24 August (Box 8C, Folder 17)
  - 1992-Teleconference materials and minutes-16 November (Box 8C, Folder 18)
  - 1993-Teleconference materials and minutes-29 November (Box 8C, Folder 19)
  - 1993-Teleconference minutes-15 December (Box 8C, Folder 20)
  - 1994-Teleconference minutes-29 March (Box 8C, Folder 21)
  - 1994-Teleconference materials and minutes-10 June (Box 8C, Folder 22)
  - 1994-Teleconference materials and minutes-27 September (Box 8C, Folder 23)
  - 1994-Teleconference materials and minutes-14 December (Box 8C, Folder 24)
  - 1995-Teleconference materials-25-27 January (Box 8C, Folder 25)
  - 1995-Teleconference materials-26 September (Box 8C, Folder 26)
  - 1997-Teleconference agenda-29 May (Box 8C, Folder 27)
- National Counselor Certification - NAADAC Certification Commission - Miscellaneous (Box 8C)
  - Miscellaneous, 1993-1996 (includes correspondence, reports, memorandums) (Box 8C, Folder 28)
- National Commission for Accreditation - Organizations (Box 9-10)
  - A.D.P.A. (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - Azcare Health Corporation (Box 9, Folder 2)
  - Conifer Park (Box 9, Folder 3)
  - CRC/AODA (Box 9, Folder 4)
  - CSTAA--Memoranda (Box 9, Folder 5)
  - Koala Center (Box 9, Folder 6)
  - The Mediplex Group (Box 9, Folder 7)
  - Mel Schulstad, Inc. (Box 9, Folder 8)
  - NAADAC (Formerly NAAC) (Box 9, Folder 9)
  - National Association of Alcoholism Treatment Programs (Box 9, Folder 10)
  - NAC--By-laws (Box 9, Folder 11)
  - NAC--Annual meetings, budget, by-laws (Box 9, Folder 12)
  - NAC--Conference call minutes--25 January 1990 - 9 March 1993 (Box 9, Folder 13)
  - NAC--Motions to Board of Directors (Box 9, Folder 14)
  - NAC--Letters, memoranda, officer rosters (Box 9, Folder 15)
  - NAC--Proposed marketing plan & organization goals (Box 9, Folder 16)
  - NAC--Results from phone survey of state certification boards--February 1993 (Box 9, Folder 17)
  - NAC--Dissolution (Box 9, Folder 18)
  - NCAADACCB--Articles of Incorporation, by-laws (Box 9, Folder 19)
  - NCAADACCB--Accreditation application package (Box 9, Folder 20-21)
  - NCAADACCB--Minutes 1989-1991 (Box 9, Folder 22)
  - NCAADACCB--Correspondence 1989 (Box 9, Folder 23)
  - NCAADACCB--Correspondence 1990 (Box 9, Folder 24)
  - NCAADACCB--Annual meeting--San Francisco, CA--3-4 October 1992 (Box 10, Folder 1)
  - NCAADACCB--Correspondence, reports, memoranda, lists (Box 10, Folder 2)
  - NCCAC--By-laws, Articles of Incorporation (Box 10, Folder 3)
  - NCCAC--Correspondence, Memos (Box 10, Folder 4)
  - NIDA--Credentialing (Box 10, Folder 5)
  - PACES (Box 10, Folder 6)
  - Salvation Army (Box 10, Folder 7)
  - Therapeutic Communities of America (Integrity) (Box 10, Folder 8)
  - USADAC (Box 10, Folder 9-10)
  - Valle Associates (Box 10, Folder 11)
  - Walter J. Finnegan Associates (Box 10, Folder 12)
- National Commission for Accreditation - Organizations--by state (Box 10-15)
  - Alabama Alcoholism and Drug Counselors Certification Board (Box 10, Folder 13-15)
  - Alaska (Box 10, Folder 16-17)
  - Alaska (Box 11, Folder 1-3)
  - Arkansas (Box 11, Folder 4)
  - California (Box 11, Folder 5)
  - Connecticut Federation of Alcoholism and Drug Abuse Counselors (Box 11, Folder 6)
  - Delaware (Box 11, Folder 7)
  - Idaho (Box 11, Folder 8)
  - Illinois (Box 11, Folder 9-11)
  - Illinois (Box 12, Folder 1-4)
  - Illinois Alcoholism Counselor Certification Board (Box 12, Folder 5-9)
  - Illinois and Long Island (Box 12, Folder 10-11)
  - Illinois Drug Abuse Counselor Certification Program (Box 13, Folder 1)
  - Illinois Substance Abuse Counselor Certification Board (Box 13, Folder 2-3)
  - Indiana (Box 13, Folder 4)
  - Louisiana (Box 13, Folder 5)
  - Maryland (Box 13, Folder 6)
  - Michigan--Office of Substance Abuse (Box 13, Folder 7)
  - Minnesota (Box 13, Folder 8)
  - Missouri (Box 13, Folder 9)
  - Nebraska (Box 13, Folder 10)
  - New Jersey (Box 13, Folder 11)
  - New Mexico (Box 13, Folder 12)
  - New York (Box 13, Folder 13)
  - Ohio Chemical Dependency Counselors Credentialing Board (Box 13, Folder 14-16)
  - Ohio Chemical Dependency Counselors Credentialing Board (Box 14, Folder 1-5)
  - Oklahoma (Box 14, Folder 6-8)
  - Oregon (Box 14, Folder 9-13)
  - South Carolina (Box 15, Folder 1)
  - South Dakota (Box 15, Folder 2)
  - South Dakota Chemical Dependency Counselors Certification Board (Box 15, Folder 3-4)
  - Tennessee (Box 15, Folder 5)
  - Texas (Box 15, Folder 6)
  - Texas Association of Alcoholism and Drug Abuse Counselors (Box 15, Folder 7)
  - Texas Certification Board of Alcoholism and Drug Abuse Counselors (Box 15, Folder 8-9)
  - Vermont (Box 15, Folder 10)
  - Washington (Box 15, Folder 11)
  - Wisconsin (Box 15, Folder 12)
- National Commission for Accreditation - Miscellaneous (Box 15)
  - Development of Certification Examination for Alcholism Counselors, Drug Abuse Counselors, and Substance Abuse Counselors (Box 15, Folder 13)
  - Performance summaries, national registry (Box 15, Folder 14)
  - Reciprocity (Box 15, Folder 15)
- Alcohol and Drug Abuse Rehabilitation Program (ADERP) - ADERP History and Reports (Box 16)
  - Virginia Commonwealth University (Box 16, Folder 1)
  - History of ADERP (Box 16, Folder 2-4)
  - ADERP--Quarterly Reports--1-5 (1975-1976) (Box 16, Folder 5)
  - ADERP--Quarterly Reports--6-12 (1976-1978) (Box 16, Folder 6)